Register of the Wolność i Niezawisłość miscellaneous records
Hoover Institution Archives
Wolność i Niezawisłość miscellaneous records
1936-1946
95046
Hoover Institution Archives
1 half-manuscript box (0.2 linear feet)
The collection is comprised of newsletters, memoranda, letters, leaflets, and flyers relating to Polish opposition to Soviet and communist forces at the end of World War II.
Wolnosc i Niezawislosc (Organization)
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical note
Wolność i Niezawisłość (WiN) (Freedom and Independence), an underground anti-communist organization, was established on September 2, 1945, in Warsaw, Poland. Its main goal was to fight communism and the Sovietification of Poland through political channels, with minimal military action. However, hostility between WiN and communist organizations, such as the Polish Ministry of Public Security, the Polish Worker’s Party, and the NKVD, often led to provocation, resulting in violence. Realizing that victory through violence was impossible, members of WiN instead chose to focus on fighting the communists through anti-communist propaganda and by providing assistance to all those who opposed the communist government.
By 1952, WiN ceased to exist, mainly due to the efforts of the Ministry of Public Security and its leader, Jakub Berman, who assassinated a number of the organization’s prominent members.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is comprised of letters, printed matter, reports, personal orders, notices, and orders of promotion, as well as a file regarding Akcja “O” (Operation “O”).
Anti-communist movements--Poland.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.
- Akcja "O" (Operation "O"), 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Akcja “O” was a large WiN anti-communist operation conducted through the use of various types of propaganda. Its main purpose was to weaken communist organizations, such as the Ministry of Public Security and the Polish Worker’s Party. The operation was also meant to inform the Polish people of the transgressions and injustices committed against them by the communist groups.
- Donosy (Accusations), circa 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 2)
- Biuletyny (Newsletters), 1944-1945 (Box-folder : 1: 3)
- Karty rozpoznawcze (Identification cards), 1942 (Box-folder : 1: 4)
- List na otoczenie (Circular), undated (Box-folder : 1: 5)
- List na upatrzonego (Letter to the target), 1944 (Box-folder : 1: 6)
- Listy członków (List of members), 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 7)
- Lusia, 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 8)
- Mapy (Maps), circa 1936-1940 (Box-folder : 1: 9)
- Polska Partia Robotnicza (Polish Workers Party), circa 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 10)
- Powiatowy Urząd Ziemski (District Land Office), 1944-1945 (Box-folder : 1: 12)
- Przepustki (Passes), 1944-1945 (Box-folder : 1: 12)
- Publikacje (Publications), 1939-1946 (Box-folder : 1: 13)
- Raporty (Reports), 1945-1946 (Box-folder : 1: 14)
- Robak, Michał, 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 15)
- Rozkazy personalne (Personal orders), 1945 (Box-folder : 1: 16)
- Rozliczenia (Settelments), 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 17)
- Szyfr (Cipher), circa 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 18)
- Według rozdzielnika (According to a dilimiter), circa 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 19)
- Wiersze (Poems), circa 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 20)
- Wnioski - odznaczenia i awanse (Decorations and promotions), 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 21)
- Zawiadomienia (Notices), 1946 (Box-folder : 1: 22)
- Fotografie (Photographs), undated (Box-folder : 1: 23)
- Różne (Miscellaneous), undated (Box-folder : 1: 24)